[SPEAKER_01]: So, this is a question about right speech.
[SPEAKER_01]: This person asks, well, I want to speak truthfully and with kindness, but in difficult conversations, I either speak too harshly or remain silent out of fear of conflict.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe I'm just overthinking this, but how can I skillfully apply right speech in such moments?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, by skillfully applying right actions beforehand.
[SPEAKER_00]: with your body.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, is your mind restrained, entained, contained, able to endure things on the right level without acting out?
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, the the field of development of your speech can become more apparent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, it's just... you just want to deal with the speech, because that's the acute issue, but failing to understand that the sole reason you swayed as much
[SPEAKER_00]: In these experiences is because the mind is not tamed enough, not contained enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you can't be purifying your speech if your actions are not purified, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because when speaking to others in a difficult situation, that's pretty intense, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you are unable to contain that intensity without spilling out through your mouth.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the reason you're unable to contain the intensity is because you haven't trained in containing intensities.
[SPEAKER_00]: Intensities of restraint and precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the whole point of containing a physical behavior, is to be able to, like, remove... remain unmoved in face of a pressuring mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mind that exerts intensity on you to do, to act, to say, to think.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, a sign of progress would be a person who is able to endure harsh speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like a person who doesn't feel the intensity.
[SPEAKER_00]: You still feel it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Feels the intensity, but...
[SPEAKER_00]: It does not make you say things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Harsh things, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're still kind.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can say kind things or appropriate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the right way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, or even if you don't say anything, at least you won't be saying anything out of that intensity, out of that pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there's really no bypass, because you can learn skillful ways of speaking in difficult situations, you know, non-violent communication and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but all that is just to manage the fact that you still have to do something on account of that intensity.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're already freaking out and now you have to manage it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to manage it, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why often in the suttas, like, it would be listed there, like, high up,
[SPEAKER_00]: In the training of the monks, it's like, it was, you know, restrained by the virtue, sense-restraint, moderate.
[SPEAKER_00]: He endures the harsh words.
[SPEAKER_00]: He bears them, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not even endures, on the right level, you know.
[SPEAKER_00]: When we talk about it, it's kind of slightly different.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, he bears them.
[SPEAKER_00]: He bears the harsh words.
[SPEAKER_00]: He bears the elements.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is... it doesn't even matter whether you're aware of the right level and what the practice is and this or that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bearing it is already development of elements and harsh words.
[SPEAKER_01]: No retorting, no speaking back... Just plain bearing.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're able to plainly bear discomfort, you'll be able to endure things on the right level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, the domain of the middle way, where things endure on their own,
[SPEAKER_00]: Where the discernment happens, where the nimittas are discerned, all of that, that can become apparent.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you can't even bear elements and words of others, it means you still have work to do before you can endure things on the right level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because often people think it's the same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, enduring things on the right level is the same just as mindless bearing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a bit deeper than...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the middle way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Patient endurance, khanti, enduring things on the right level as khanti, it's the... it's exactly where the middle way is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's where you recognize things arising on their own, you see the extent of the intensity and the pressure they exert, your mind exerts on you, and you are unmoved by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're enduring it, as in enduring the lack of
[SPEAKER_00]: The tameness in this animal, in that particular instance, but you're seeing the full extent of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's on the right level of your correct, right perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, for that, you need to work your way up.
[SPEAKER_00]: And when you fall from that,
[SPEAKER_00]: When you lose that perspective, you lose that right... right level, well, you fall back on being able to bear the intensity of the animal without compromising your situation further through your actions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's a... it's a fail-safe.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, when that sort of... when the animal calms down somewhat, you regain the perspective.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's how even when you fail to endure things on the right level, you're still held up by virtue, by the aggregate of virtue, by being able to bear discomfort, elements, without disintegrating.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, obviously, without discerning and understanding the nature of contact, passa, pressure, intensity, whatever way you want to translate it,
[SPEAKER_00]: Bearing, like, restraint and virtue and stuff, will never automatically or mechanically or magically take you to the level of enduring things on the right level, in terms of having a perspective and not too much, not too little.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: For that, you need to discern.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, obviously, there will be no discernment taking place, if you're not even able to practice basic
[SPEAKER_00]: Bearing of the mental pressure that precepts put on you, elements, words of others, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: bearing, not acting out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's obviously some overlap in the development.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not like black and white where it becomes enduring, but it's not the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that actually leads me to another question that I... Before his awakening, the Bodhisattva practiced extreme asceticism and later said it was futile.
[SPEAKER_01]: The Buddha later said that was futile.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, it seems to me like it was necessary in some way for him to go through that, like it did benefit him in some way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Could he have realized dhamma without those years of kind of hardship, you know?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, eh... it was necessary for him in a sense that he had to go through trial and error in order to arrive at that which was left, that middle way.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it was necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: Was it necessary in terms of specifically doing that?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, absolutely not.
[SPEAKER_00]: That was not necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, having through trial and error arrived at neither too much nor too little, he then taught that as the way to enlightenment to those now who can practice on account of his teaching.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, it was necessary for him because he was the first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Subsequently, everybody else cannot be that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, with the right instruction that he conveyed, then, doing those things, it's completely unnecessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: However, where the line of asceticism is, that's not something that's just, like, universally true for everybody.
[SPEAKER_00]: That depends on a person.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why, if you know what the middle way is, if you know where the enduring things on the right level is, that's your tune, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the melody, that's the... the... the harmony you want to be protecting and cultivating.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes increasing
[SPEAKER_00]: Asceticism, what can be perceived as asceticism externally, can contribute to maintenance of that middle way, of that right level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sometimes increasing ascetic practices can actually be detrimental to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why when when Devadatta was requesting from the Buddha to make these ascetic dhūtangas mandatory for everybody, because they're factually inspiring to people, make everybody want to practice, like for future generations, he said, no, let those who want to do it, do it, and those who don't want to do it, not do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, let those who know that it's beneficial
[SPEAKER_00]: for their endurance on the right level, for their middle way, let them do it, and let those who know that it's unbeneficial, not do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because doing it blindly will take you away from the right melody, from the right tune.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just saying, well, I'll put up with hardships and that will give me that... Yeah, and that's why I say, why?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, I won't put up with hardship.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why?
[SPEAKER_00]: The decision, whether you do it or not, should be coming from the recognition of where the practice is, where the right endurance is.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's maintaining it, clarifying it, do it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If it's obscuring it, taking you away from it, then don't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, that you... some people require a certain amount of stress to keep things in perspective, actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Some people require none, but you can't... you can't just pre-decide that for yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: How much is... And even as the Buddha himself, before, as a bodhisattva, he went through all these things, and when he pretty much ran out of options, he tried everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's nothing that he hasn't tried.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that was necessary for him to then revisit and remember his jhāna experience before he left the household life.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, he would not have even considered it if there were still things that were left for him that he hasn't tried.
[SPEAKER_00]: Towards enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, by the way, since we are at that, talking about it, I think, like, the common notion is, oh, he experienced jhāna as a child or something, but it's completely unsupported by the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think they came with, like, jātakas and later commentaries, I don't know exactly where, the whole idea of he was a young boy under a tree, entering jhāna kind of just spontaneously.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was like innocence of a child.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah, kind of.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, basically, kind of... and it...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it came... well, almost certainly came from the commentaries, but I think it... it became almost like a pivotal point for the modern views of the special experiences in meditation and jhāna, because, look, it happened to the Buddha randomly as a child, without restraint, without understanding sensuality and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: And no sutta ever says that.
[SPEAKER_00]: He says he remembers under an apple tree, before in his life, that he experienced this and thought, how about I pursue that and see where it takes me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is no mention that he was a child.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, there was the... was it Agama or some Tibetan parallels to that?
[SPEAKER_00]: I think it might have been some other Tibetan or Chinese parallel.
[SPEAKER_00]: To that, eh... one of the suttas that mentioned that, and it elaborates on that whole story, whereby, not just that he wasn't a child, it was shortly before him leaving the household life, after, basically, he already seen a sick, a dead, a sick man, old man and a dead man.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he already... his mind already fully experienced this passion.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there's actually a sutta in Pali Nikaya where it says that, while he was still a bodhisattva, before he left his home, after encountering the sick, aging and dead man, the intoxication with life, sensuality, youth, left him.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even before he went out and became a renunciate to seek enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: So, this Chinese parallel elaborates actually on that story, whereby his father has already had suspicions that he wants to leave the kingdom and become a renunciate, wandering ascetic.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he sent him to this village that was under their kind of
[SPEAKER_00]: How do you call it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Rulership.
[SPEAKER_00]: Rulership.
[SPEAKER_00]: Basically, to incite him to rule because that it's going to be his.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of the people there are his subjects of his kingdom and he should go and attend to the work they were doing and just basically get him re-involved.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he went there and then he saw all these kind of slaves and people just suffering, working hard in very rough conditions and he says, who do you belong to?
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, who is this like?
[SPEAKER_00]: He says, we belong to you, sir.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, we work for your kingdom.
[SPEAKER_00]: We are yours.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he says, okay, well, from now on, from this day onwards, you're free men, just leave.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he basically, he was so shocked to see the harshness of your average person's life.
[SPEAKER_00]: He went basically... he dismissed them and went under a tree, under a rose apple tree or whatever it's translated.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dispassionate.
[SPEAKER_00]: Completely dispassionate, even more turned away from the life.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where he entered jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's what he remembered after trying all these extremely amplified practices of asceticism and this and that to get...
[SPEAKER_00]: He realized, hold on, I remember that experience when actually there was no hindrances,
[SPEAKER_00]: The right level was there, the perfect tune was just ongoing, and it was on the basis of complete dispassion and disenchantment.
[SPEAKER_00]: There was nothing tying him to the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: How about I pursue that further?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he realized that's the way to enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because up until that point... See, all the ascetic practices, they require passion.
[SPEAKER_00]: And he didn't question that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because he thought those practices are valid in and of themselves, and they'll do the work for him.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there is no way you will be committing to the extreme levels of self-modification without that hard center of passion driving you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, he remembered the experience when his mind was completely passionless, completely disenchanted, turned away, not leaning on to anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there was the experience of jhāna.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's something like, although it's something like a, as I said, Tibetan or a Chinese parallel, it ties in with that other actual sutta, where he did say that these intoxications left him even before he left the home.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, he was already free from centrality, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said, since he left the home, he hasn't had the central thought, even way before he became the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, just to kind of re-illustrate that point, so people don't think
[SPEAKER_00]: These things happen magically, because some later commentary, they thought, oh, he must have been a kid or something.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just didn't understand what had happened.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, he didn't understand the full extent of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as I said, like, he obviously thought that the ascetic practices, this amplified, drier force and committing to the practices, is more of that dispassion that he was doing under the apple tree.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when he realized that it isn't...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just the opposite.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, he thought, oh, that was too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, sensuality, connection to the world, concern with the world, abandon all of that, you reach the middle level of dispassion in regard to both directions.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then he thought, abandoning the world is good, so how about I go even further and start forcing this, so I get to that enlightenment.
[SPEAKER_00]: And came to the brink of death and realized, hold on, actually, no, now there's passion again.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, let me go back, retrace my step, until there is no passion and stop there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there was the first jhāna, there was the rose apple tree experience, there was enduring things on the right level.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now you stick to that, and that's then what he thought, what he was teaching afterwards for the rest of his life.
[SPEAKER_00]: How to get to that, through the Noble Eightfold Path, and stay there, and protect it, and cultivate it, until your work is done.